<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Character of the Parliament, commonly called the Rump, &amp;c., begun November 23, in the year 1640 with a short account of some of their proceedings.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31740</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C2026A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7601</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12272734</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12272734</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58333</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31740)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58333)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 309:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Character of the Parliament, commonly called the Rump, &amp;c., begun November 23, in the year 1640 with a short account of some of their proceedings.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>iv, 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and sold by the booksellers of London,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1660]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58333:1"/>
            <p>THE CHARACTER OF THE PARLIAMENT, Commonly called the <hi>Rump,</hi> &amp;c. Begun <hi>November</hi> 23. in the Year 1640. With a ſhort ACCOUNT of ſome of their PROCEEDINGS.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Ille nefaſto te poſuit die</l>
               <l>— in nepotum</l>
               <l>Perniciem, opprobrium<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Pagi.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>HORACE.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Hinc uſura vorax, avidum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> in tempore faenus, &amp; concuſſa fides, &amp; multis utile Bellum,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>LUCAN</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed and Sold by the Bookſellers of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:58333:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58333:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HERE are few Men of Judgment, Candor, and Impartiality, who will not allow a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, conſiſting of King and Parliament, to be the beſt Conſtitution in the World. <hi>France, Spain, Denmark, Sweden, Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cily,</hi> and ſome other Kingdoms, had once this Advantage, but unfortunately loſt it; ſome by Faction, others by being Conquered; and others, by a National depravity of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, joined to the Ambition of Princes, and the Intrigues of their Miniſters. <hi>We</hi> of theſe Iſlands are now left the laſt, who enjoy this Bleſſing in any Perfection; and we may ſtill preſerve it pure and entire, if we can but retain ſome De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of the Virtue of our Anceſtors. But we ſhould be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful what Perſons we chooſe to Repreſent us in Parliament; for, if (according to the vulgar Maxim in the Schools.) <hi>Corruptio optimi eſt Peſſima,</hi> a CORRUPT <hi>Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament</hi> would then, of all Evils in Government, be the Greateſt; and exceed the worſt Tyranny in a ſingle Perſon. An abſolute Prince might be Cruel, Rapacious, Covetous, a Diſſipater of the Publick Treaſure, an Enemy of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and it would be very bad: But all this would be nothing, when compared to a <hi>Mob</hi> of ſuch Tyrants, moſt of them with the ſame Diſpoſitions, and every way like that greater one, only the more provoking, as in their Perſons they would be more contemptible, nor is this a Thing not to be ſuppoſed. Our Hiſtory furniſheth us with an Inſtance of a Parliament of that kind; which is here undertaken to be deſcribed to the Publick, in one unmixed View; both
<pb n="iv" facs="tcp:58333:3"/>becauſe this hath not been yet done by any one, that I know of; and alſo, that a Proſpect of it in this manner, may poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly give our Country-Men, a full Notion, of how great Conſequence it is to them, to be extreamly cautious whom they truſt at any time to be their <hi>Repreſentatives.</hi> Here they may have before their Eyes, what Abuſes a CORRUPT <hi>Parliament</hi> is capable of. The Writer, in putting his Thoughts together on this Subject, has ſet himſelf a Rule to keep Religoiuſly to the Hiſtory of the Men and the Times, and not to indulge himſelf or the Reader in charging any Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter too much, or deviating from the Truth, to make the Story more agreeable. The Facts and Characters are all of them to be found, either in my Lord <hi>Clarendon, Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock, Ruſhworth,</hi> Sir <hi>Philip Warwick, Ludlow, Hobbs,</hi> or ſome other Writer of thoſe Times: But many Paſſages are omitted for the Sake of Brevity, or through Forgetfulneſs, or becauſe they did not exactly fall in with the general De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign: And ſuch as are mentioned, are not always conſidered in the order of Time in which they happened. True it is, ſome few of the Things here imputed to the Parliament, were not their immediate and direct Act; but, which is much the ſame thing, though not all done by them, they were all done in their way, in treading their Paths, and by a Power derived from them. The greateſt <hi>Scelerates</hi> had either their expreſs Orders, their Approbation or Example and Authority, to plead for the worſt Crimes then committed.</p>
            <p>BY what Means and Degrees theſe Pretended Patriots arrived to the height of Wickedneſs, and begat ſo great Irreverence towards their own Perſons and Characters, is here endeavoured to be explained, and may poſſibly be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to theſe, who may not elſewhere have obſerved the Series of their Tranſactions; nor the Period, when proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they became dignified with the Title of the <hi>Rump;</hi> which was, when they had ſubverted all the honeſt Ends and Purpoſes of Parliaments, and when they ſate by Virtue of their <hi>own Choice and Power,</hi> and not by the <hi>Free Election</hi> of their <hi>Country.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:58333:3"/>
            <head>THE CHARACTER OF THE PARLIAMENT, Commonly call'd the <hi>Rump.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS famous <hi>Parliament,</hi> which Sate ſo long, did ſo much Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, and involved the three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms in Guilt and Miſery, met at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> the 3d of <hi>November,</hi> 1640. Through the Miſrepreſentations of thoſe about the King, his Majeſty unluckily thought fit to part with the preceding Parliament upon ill
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:58333:4"/>Terms, and before he had Time to know them, which was thought a very impolitick Step, to ſay no worſe of it. They were Men of Moderation, and zealous for the Publick Good, and were the Reverſe of their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors; who never ceas'd 'till they drew upon theſe Nations infinite Calamities, and Diſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, and even Contempt upon the very Name of a Houſe of COMMONS.</p>
            <p>AMONG many illegal and more weak Things, then committed in the Adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Affairs, none could be worſe judged, than that Precipitate Act of the Court; which ſtruck, with Concern and Indignation, all who had a due Attention to his Majeſty's Service, and Regard for the Conſtitution of the Realm. But it was the Subject of Joy and Triumph to the Men of turbulent Spirits; to the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Church, and of Peace; to thoſe, who long'd for nothing more than to throw the State into Confuſion, in hopes to repair their ſhattered Fortunes, to acquire Wealth and Power; or to glut their Malice and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge. And it muſt be owned, the Succeſs anſwered beyond their moſt extravagant Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations: A great Part of their Purpoſes, and even Wiſhes, having been fatally effected, and many of the chief Managers having crept in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to high Stations, purloined Titles, and amaſſed immenſe Sums, who from their Birth, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:58333:4"/>or Qualifications, could reaſonably have aſpired no higher, than to the meaneſt Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <p>FROM Motives, and by Perſons, ſuch as theſe, the Elections could not but be carried on very irregularly. The Factious were Men of Craft and Induſtry, and ſtuck at nothing to carry their Point. Returns were made of Perſons to ſerve for Places, where their Names had never been heard of before; and, where Bribes and Artifices, to debauch the Minds of the Electors and the Returning Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, would not prevail, Violence ſucceeded. Neither was this the worſt of the Caſe. When the Houſe of Commons met, and by thoſe and other Means, the Majority was clearly on the ſide of the <hi>Faction,</hi> they turned out, and put in whom they thought proper, without any ſort of Modeſty, or the leaſt attention to the eſtabliſh'd Rules of the Houſe, or to the manifeſt Juſtice of the Cauſe. Thus very many, againſt the Conſent, and without the Knowledge of their Country, aſſumed to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the Title of its Repreſentatives, which yet was not ordinarily objected to them as any Crime; ſo much did their Conduct, as Members of the Houſe, obſcure the Reproach of their having diſhonourably intruded into it.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:58333:5"/>
            <p>IT is true, a great Part of this foul Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement, in point of Elections, happen'd in proceſs of Time, when they were grown Old and Hardened in Corruptions of all Kinds; when they had loſt the Remembrance of Right and Wrong; but it is alſo true, that even in the Infancy of their Power, the ſame Spirit prevail'd, and they ſet out with the Aſſurance of thoſe, who had abandon'd all Decency and Remorſe. The difference was, it was Paſſion, and Rage, and Madneſs in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning: Afterwards, it was Phlegmatick, impudent Villany, and Corruption.</p>
            <p>YET, it ought always to be remembred, that there were Men of that Houſe, of as great Worth, Integrity, and Abilities, as have ſate in any Parliament whatever: Men, who were Proof againſt all Temptations of Gain, and not to be over-awed by Threats, or the Torrent that then raged. But theſe were out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numbered by People of different Views, dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Principles: The Majority was a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound of Pretenders to Zeal againſt Popery, of real Atheiſts, of profeſſed Republicans, of weak and Ignorant Slaves to the Managers, and above all, of wretched Mercenaries, who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted their Conſcience, and ſold their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try for their Daily Pay.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:58333:5"/>
            <p>THE Leaders of this Band of Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors againſt their Country deſerve to be delivered down to Poſterity, with all poſſible Marks of Infamy: But becauſe Deſcendants may attone for the Wickedneſs (as they often degenerate from the Virtue) of their Anceſtors, the Names of thoſe Perſons ſhall at preſent be paſſed over in Silence. Yet at the ſame Time, it may not be altogether unſeaſonable to sketch out the Characters of ſome few of the moſt No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious, that we may look back and ſee, what ſort of Perſons thoſe were, who had both the Will and Power to <hi>impoveriſh</hi> the <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick,</hi> and enſlave their Native Country; that if for the future any <hi>others</hi> ſhould unhappily ariſe with the ſame Diſpoſitions and Talents, the Reſemblance might be obſerv'd time enough to prevent a Parallel in the Story every way.</p>
            <p>ONE of theſe was a <hi>Gentleman,</hi> well known in thoſe Times, both on the Score of his Parts, which were competently adapted to the Mechanical Part of Buſineſs, and alſo of ſome Diſgrace, he had undergone from the late Men in Power; which, when that Power devolved into other Hands, gave him a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to ſet up for a <hi>Sufferer.</hi> He ſpoke in the Houſe with great readineſs, and at all Times with a certain appearing Frankneſs, in his manner of expreſſing himſelf, that was not
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58333:6"/>diſagreeable. No Man ſpoke more than he of Concern for the <hi>Publick;</hi> no Man had the Publick leſs at Heart; but it ſerv'd his Purpoſe, as it furniſh'd him with Popular Topicks for Harrangues, and was likewiſe a convenient Prey for him and his hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry Creatures. He was a bold Undertaker in Buſineſs; not eaſily diſcourag'd by the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty of the Work, and never to be put out of Countenance at the foulneſs of it. But his chief Excellence conſiſted in the dexterous Application of Lies to his ſeveral Purpoſes; and thoſe he could frame extempore, and with that undaunted Aſſurance, they were of great Service to him at particular Seaſons; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the too frequent Uſe of them, and his laughing at Truth, openly and wantonly, contributed no leſs to the diſcovery of his defect in Judgment, than his ſnatching at all Opportunities to get Money, betrayed the Weakneſs and Impotence of his Mind. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, his Influence in the <hi>Houſe</hi> was great: From the Senſe of what pleaſed himſelf beſt, he knew how to gain others; and he was the better qualified for the Times, and for the Part he had to act, being wholly void of Shame, and as entirely undiſturbed with any Fumes or Principles of Virtue, Honour or Religion; as free in himſelf from all Aproaches towards Compaſſion or Humanity.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:58333:6"/>
            <p>A <hi>ſecond</hi> of theſe was a <hi>Gentleman</hi> of good Extraction, liberal Education, and of ſome Learning. From the Company he had kept in his younger Years, and from his manner of Life, he had contracted an inveterate Malice againſt the Church, and imbibed early Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples againſt Monarchy: Though no Man went farther than he, in the Support and promoting of the moſt lawleſs Acts of Tyranny, when he had his Share of Power. He had been bred up to the Profeſſion of Arms, and had got ſome Reputation that way, which he quickly loſt, by the unſoldierly Defence and <hi>Surrender</hi> of a <hi>Town</hi> of Importance: For this ill Conduct he was accuſed, and might have Suffer'd, if he had not been befriended by the <hi>General,</hi> who lived to repent his good Nature, to a Man, never very ſenſible of Favours or Benefits. That Gentleman betook himſelf afterwards to another kind of Life, and got one of the <hi>Seals</hi> into his Poſſeſſion, which he uſed to ill Purpoſes enough, but always with good Manners, which was peculiar to him. Not being well fixed in any Form of Government, he ran into many wild Schemes, and was rather a Builder of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Wealths, than a Member of any one. It was conjectured he had a Tincture of Enthuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſm in his Compoſition, which, if true, might account for part of his Life, and perhaps be thought ſome extenuation of ſeveral things he had been guilty of, to the Prejudice of his
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58333:7"/>Country, to which, perhaps, few Men really wiſh'd better, than he.</p>
            <p>ANOTHER of theſe, and, it may be; one of the moſt outragious of the whole <hi>Sett,</hi> was an <hi>Officer</hi> of mean Parts and Parentage; a meddling, bluſtring Fellow, determined, and very diligent: Conceited, Undertaking, inca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of offering any Reaſons to convince o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, or of comprehending Reaſon, ſo as to be perſwaded himſelf. By the extraordinary Favour of the <hi>General,</hi> to whom lic had been <hi>Uſeful</hi> in <hi>ſeveral Capacities,</hi> he had made his way, from being a <hi>Subaltern,</hi> in a few Years, to one of the higheſt Poſts in the Army; and in every Poſt, he ſtill ſhewed great uneaſineſs, as if the Place were not big enough to hold him, and that he could not breathe, until he got higher; which made him preſs and buſtle and affront every thing in his way. He was Servile in his Applications to thoſe who could advance him, and no Man endeavoured to make his Court more than he, or did it with a worſe Grace. So that his Ambition was unmeaſurable, but misbecame him: And it was obſerved of him by one of the ſame Side, who was no bad Obſerver of Men, That <hi>he was a Clown in fine Cloaths;</hi> intimating, how uncouthly any thing of Grandeur ſat upon him.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:58333:7"/>
            <p>WHEN the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Commons</hi> became ſilled with <hi>Soldiers,</hi> he got himſelf returned to ſerve for a Borough, and acted the ſame Part in the Houſe, he had done out of it; that is, he was reſtleſs in his Motions, and brutal in his Opinions; and tho' he often appeared more buſie, than he really was, he never could ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear more Brutal. If at any Time an unjuſt Propoſition, that might lay whole Countries waſte, was to be made in the Houſe, he was ſo apprehenſive of its failing, he would run every where to Summon the <hi>Poſſe,</hi> and take upon himſelf the Office of <hi>Muſter-Maſter-General</hi> of the Party: And then if by great accident, the Houſe ſeemed inclined to come into an Act leſs ill-natured than uſual, it would put him out of all Patience, and he would ſhew the utmoſt diſquiet, being unable to keep his Countenance, or to ſit ſtill in his Place. Ingratitude was ſo much a part of his Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter, it was looked upon with the Indulgence People allow for natural Infirmities, which are not to be cured. His Underſtanding was confuſed and muddy; ſo he never troubled his Head about Notions, or Schemes, or Laws of Government; all which he reſolved into <hi>Force:</hi> Conſequently his Politicks, as his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, were thoſe of a <hi>Dragoon,</hi> to oppreſs and Plunder where he could; which he performed with the moſt punctual Diſcipline, without Bowels, or Mercy.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:58333:8"/>
            <p>FROM him a good deal of the Spirit of the Officers of thoſe Times may be collected: Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho' they differed in many other Particulars, yet in thoſe of Rapine, Plunder, and Inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, they ſeemed to agree very well, and to be uniform in their Principles, if we may ſo call them.</p>
            <p>A fourth of the <hi>Ephorí</hi> was the then <hi>Solli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citor General,</hi> a Man of all others the leaſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miable: He was deſcended of an antient Family by an indirect Line; was extremely formal, proud, and moroſe; converſed with few, and had a certain pedantick manner of declaring his own Opinion, and expreſſing a Contempt of that of all others; which, perhaps ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times impoſed upon thoſe, who knew no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than himſelf, and might have gained him the little Repute he had, of Skill in his Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And that which was very particular, his Self-Sufficiency was ſo entire, that whatever he advanced, he would believe to be right; and he would advance ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd Arguments in Point of Law, upon a ſuppoſition of their receiving a Sanction from him: By which means, he would wreſt the Law in a very ſhameleſs manner. The reſt of his Brethren of the Law he ſurpaſſed in ill Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Sowerneſs, and Inhumanity: Yet his predo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minant Quality was Inſolence; which ſhone in every Act and Motion of his Life, in his
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:58333:8"/>Air, his Geſtures, his Words, and particularly in his Looks: All which rendered him not leſs inſupportable in Buſineſs, than he was in his own Family, where he was an abſolute Lord and Tyrant. No wonder if a Perſon of his Frame, was a very evil Inſtrument in tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Times, and eſpecially when Bribery ran higheſt; ſince it was well known, no Man's Ears, and Hands, and Heart, were more open than his, to Gain.</p>
            <p>THERE was indeed, another of the ſame Fraternity, but of a different Temper, who had his Hands as deep as any Man, where there was room, either for his Advice or Aſſiſtance, in moſt Acts of Violence, and barefaced Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption. He had the Appearance of gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in his Carriage, and had been formerly looked upon as no ill-natured Man. In the more innocent part of his Life, he had aſſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated himſelf with Perſons of other Principles, than thoſe of his new Friends, and had car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried thoſe Principles, at leaſt as high as any Man; but no ſooner did he change Sides, than he ſeemed to change Nature; and as if he had taken every Man of thoſe, whom he deſerted, for a living and laſting Reproach to him, he proſecuted them with an hoſtile Fury, and at their Expence, made himſelf as acceptable as he could, to his new Companions; to whom he had devoted himſelf, Soul and Body. Inſomuch, that Juſtice was never worſe adminiſtered, nor
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58333:9"/>partiality more openly <hi>exalted on the Bench,</hi> than in his Time. The Fact was; His inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate deſire to gain Credit with the Party and Money by that Credit; being inflamed by a malign hatred of his old Friends, he behaved himſelf like a mad Man, even in private Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, wherever the Intereſt of any one of the Party was concerned: And after he had gone thro' moſt of the Drudgery his Maſters expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted from him, he was found out by them to be a Man but of ordinary Abilities, and one proper to be Diſavowed as they ſhould ſee Occaſion.</p>
            <p>THERE was another Lawyer of the Party in the Houſe, of a much better Repute than either of the former. He was a Man of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in his Profeſſion, had made a good Figure at the <hi>Bar,</hi> and had Sate in former Parliaments with Approbation; but being no good Judge of Men, and not always ſteady, he was made uſe of to ſerve Purpoſes he did not intend, and concurred with Perſons, and in Things, he did not like. His Name in the Beginning was of uſe to the Managers, altho' he did not long continue to promote their Schemes. And here once for all it may be proper to be obſerved, that many contributed with all their Might and Main to the firſt Confuſions, who afterwards became ſenſible of their Error, and would have Retreated; but they found it
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58333:9"/>was very difficult to wear off bad Company, and that all, who have a Power to do Ill, have not the ſame to do Good.</p>
            <p>BUT far from any Remorſe was a <hi>Yorkſhire</hi> Man, of as eminently bad Qualities, as any one whatever: He was opinionative, and a boaſter of his Talents, which were neither quite ſo bad as ſome thought them, nor in any degree ſo good as he fancied, but might have paſſed for tolerable, if he had been content to have med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led only with Things within his Sphere. But his Ambition was active, and he procured an Employment, to which he was in no Senſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual, having neither clearneſs, nor Courage, nor Fidelity, nor Uncorruptedneſs, nor Skill enough to diſguiſe his notorious defect in all the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; ſo he became a very early rank Sinner, and ſtands foremoſt in the Liſt of the moſt guilty of thoſe Times. With a Deſign to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive others, he was out-witted himſelf, and by an odd turn, was accuſed by thoſe, with whom he had been an <hi>Accomplice</hi> in many Crimes: When he was to plead for himſelf, he grew
<note n="*" place="bottom">Lord <hi>Clarendon.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>diſtracted</hi> between <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Fear,</hi> and <hi>talked confuſedly of the Truſt repoſed in him,</hi> and of his honeſt Intentions; which was ſuch Language for him to uſe, it provoked the general Indignation of all Men. He was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the <hi>Tower,</hi> and condemned, and the <hi>Circumſtances</hi> were ſuch, that the <hi>immaiate
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58333:10"/>Hand of Almighty God could not but appear in it to all Men, who knew his Nature, Humour, and</hi> TRANSACTIONS.</p>
            <p>ANOTHER was a Gentleman of the <hi>Weſt</hi> of <hi>England</hi> of a good Eſtate, but no otherwiſe remarkable, than as a thorough Slave to the Party, of which he imagined himſelf a Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. He was a ſtupid, though frequent Speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in the Houſe; but what made him heard with the better attention, he would clap together a Parcel of ſuch odd Blunders, as would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke the graveſt Men to Mirth: Then he was always to be counted upon for a Sure Man; he had moreover a venemous diſlike of the Church, which was a Merit; and tho' to chuſe, he would have been glad to be a Gainer by an unjuſt or cruel Propoſition, yet rather than not be engaged in any thing of that Nature, he was ready to ſerve according to the beſt of his Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents (which was noiſe) upon the Foot of a Volunteer.</p>
            <p>I had almoſt forgot the <hi>Speaker</hi> of the Houſe, who was a ſuperficial proud Man, and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velouſly delighted with the Enſigns and Parade of his Place; of which he was ſaid to be tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably capable, by having applyed himſelf to the ſtudy of the Records, and Journals of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Beſides, his was a gainful Poſt, and he loved Money to exceſs; ſo the poor Man continued to keep it, amidſt many Changes, and under
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58333:10"/>ſeveral Maſters, until he and the Mace, were both turned out together, and became the deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of all People, who had ſeen to what Uſes they had both been put.</p>
            <p>I cannot omit taking notice of two others, who tho' of no Conſequence in themſelves, yet oftentimes, by either having Propoſitions put into their Mouths, or by ſeconding ſome of the others, made a ſort of a Figure in the Houſe. One of theſe was a <hi>Juſtice of Peace</hi> for <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> and <hi>Middleſex;</hi> who from the Buſineſs of that Poſt, which he exceedingly liked, both for the Buſineſs and the Gain, had paſſed a great part of his time among Strollers and Pick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pockets, and thence contracted ſome ſimilitude in their Stile, Manners, and Honeſty; which enabled him to be very vexatious, where his Authority was Supreme, and troubleſome elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, by an impertinent Zeal, under the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of a weak Head. Yet ſuch was the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence of the Party towards a faſt Friend, they frequently careſſed the Man, and ſuſtained his Follies, (wherein he abounded) at the ſame time that he was their Jeſt and Sport, even to a Proverb.</p>
            <p>THE other was one of thoſe we call half-witted: He was abſurd and bold in Diſcourſe, but in every other way a complete Coward. He was at firſt very much cheriſhed by them, becauſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:58333:11"/>he would ſay things no body elſe cared to ſay; and becauſe when they had a Mind to tire the Houſe out, they could ſet him to talk Nonſenſe, which he would pour forth upon any Subject, with great Eaſe, and Earneſtneſs, and Eloquence, for Hours together, and yet without leaving the Hearers a poſſibility of gueſſing at his Meaning, and even without underſtanding himſelf, what he would be at; which tho' a trifling Circumſtance, was often of ſingular Service to them.</p>
            <p>THERE were likewiſe ſeveral others of Note, who had a conſiderable Share in the Tranſactions and Wickedneſs of the Times, and <hi>One</hi> particularly (of a higher Orb) to whoſe Power, Craft, profound Diſſimularion, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable Temper, and Avarice not to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated, was owing as much Miſchief, as to any one Man in that, or any other Age. But con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering how miſerable a Spectacle he afterwards became, being haunted by a <hi>Demon</hi> in his <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom,</hi> and having out lived a very good Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, it would be pity to ſay more of him in this place. The other Perſons already taken notice of, were ſome of the moſt perſevering Sinners, and are ſufficient to give us a view of the Genius and Diſpoſition of the Heads of an Aſſembly, which one would think could hardly be parallelled in the Hiſtories of any Time or Country.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:58333:11"/>
            <p>BESIDES theſe, they had a Number of Hirelings, conſtant in Attendance, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd to call out, <hi>The Queſtion, The Queſtion,</hi> when ever it was neceſſary, with Clamor, to drown the Arguments of their Opponents, and by Numbers, to carry what they intended.</p>
            <p>THEY had alſo, beſides their Numbers, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Artiſices to render the Houſe as Pliant as they could wiſh. Several of their own Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers at once they got confined and impriſoned; many they threatned and frighted from attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and in the height of their Glory, they bore Contradiction with an Impatience, as if it were a Crime to controul them. This brings to Mind a Story, among ſeveral others, to exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plifie both their Cunning, and the Pride of their Hearts. The Houſe was in a warm Debate of an Affair, which the Managers had much at Heart, and carried at length, to the irreparable Damage of their Country; but it met with vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous oppoſition; particulary from a <hi>Gentleman</hi> of great Reputation, much eſteem'd every where, and terrible in the Houſe to thoſe People. In the Argument of that Day, he happened to drop an Expreſſion, that ſerv'd them for a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Clamor againſt him: this Expreſſion one of their Members, who was always willing to indulge his ſpite, and merit a Place or Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, took notice of, and complained of its Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regularity: For which the other, he ſaid, ought to <hi>withdraw;</hi> which begate another long De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:58333:12"/>The Concluſion was; After much Paſſion from the angry Men, which ſhewed how ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely offenſive that Perſon was to them, he was ordered to <hi>withdraw,</hi> and to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the <hi>Tower;</hi> whereby they inſpired new audacity into their Friends, they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged on an old Enemy, they got rid of a troubleſome Gueſt, and endeavoured to warn others, not to provoke their Vengeance and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice.</p>
            <p>No ſooner did the Houſe meet, than it was obvious enough with how little Temper, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, or Juſtice, they were likely to proceed. The Nation required Peace, that Men's Minds might be calmed; therefore the Party ran into Violences.
<note place="margin">A Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee for Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Affairs.</note> They began with <hi>Impeachments,</hi> in order to which, a <hi>Committee</hi> was appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to find out, or rather to make Miſdemea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and High-Treaſon: Nor were the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee</hi> wanting to their Buſineſs: Informers were encourag'd, Papers ſearch'd, Words tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured, and Actions miſrepreſented; and after a moſt Laborious Enquiry, they brought forth a real Juſtiſication of the Perſons accuſed. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, they had Strength enough in the Houſe thereupon to carry the <hi>Impeachments,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> and they ſtill gave out they had ſurther Diſcoveries to make, until ſome who ſaw their aim, and knew they had Power to compaſs it, thought it high time to provide for their own Safety, by not truſting their Lives and Honour in the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:58333:12"/>Power of Men, who thirſted after the Blood of the greateſt Perſons in the Kingdom, and who had no Honour to loſe in the purſuit.</p>
            <p>IT cannot be contended, but that Impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are a very proper reſource againſt the Power of Miniſters and Favourites. It is one of the moſt glorious Remains of our Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that Criminals, how ſubtle ſoever, and however protected by an eaſie or a vicious Prince, may be reached in a Parliamentary way; which Method, in ſome Caſes, is the beſt, and perhaps the only one, of coming at them. For Example, A Privy Councellor ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſeth his Maſter to enter into a <hi>War,</hi> without Provocation, deſtructive of the Trade and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of his Country, and contrary to Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Faith confirmed by ſolemn Treaties: A <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſite</hi> contrives a <hi>Project</hi> to enrich the <hi>Minions</hi> of a Court, at the Expence, and to the Ruin of many Families; a <hi>Truſtee</hi> for the <hi>Publick</hi> becomes an <hi>Advocate,</hi> and <hi>Champion</hi> for the <hi>Pillagers</hi> of it; or a <hi>Miniſter</hi> of State lays a Scheme, or ſigns an Order, that ſhall famiſh Thouſands of Innocent People. In one, or all of theſe and the like Caſes, where perhaps the Guilty cannot be affected in the common courſe of Law, and yet deſerve to be ſignalized by Exemplary Puniſhment, as eternal Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of CORRUPTION, and likewiſe of National Juſtice; it is the Duty of the <hi>Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatives</hi> of the <hi>Commons</hi> of <hi>England</hi> to Impeach
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:58333:13"/>the Offenders; and it is the higheſt Breach of Truſt in them, not thus to exert the Rights of the People, when call'd upon by ſuch enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Crimes, and by the <hi>Sufferings</hi> of their Country-men.</p>
            <p>BUT on the other Hand, the Priviledge of the Commons to Impeach, ought not to be proſtituted on ſlight Pretences, or to gratiſie the Spleen of this or that Man, or Party. And in the Caſe before us, of thoſe <hi>unhappy Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachments,</hi> which created ſo much ill Blood in the Nation, and promoted ſo faſt the enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Miſchiefs, they were not only ill-tim'd, and fatal in their Fruits, but alſo wholly without Grounds, unleſs to have ſerved ones Prince and ones Country, ought to have been imputed for Crimes.</p>
            <p>THE Perſons accuſed could not be thought Guilty, even by their Adverſaries, of betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Truſt, of Sacrificing the True <hi>Engliſh</hi> Intereſt to that of Foreigners, or of any ſort of <hi>Bribery, Corruption,</hi> or <hi>Rapine.</hi> But their Crimes were, They were faithful Servants of the Crown, and loved their Country: They were known to be averſe from all Schemes of private Gain, and abhorred the Thought of any Innovations <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>her in Church or State. It therefore became the Intereſt, as it was the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination, of the governing Party, to remove out of their way ſuch Obſtacles to their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns; and becauſe there was not the leaſt
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:58333:13"/>ground in point of Law, to proceed upon againſt them, they fell upon <hi>Impeachments,</hi> as the moſt artful way to conceal the Weakneſs of their Accuſation, and at the ſame time to raiſe that ferment, which was ſo neceſſary to their further Views,</p>
            <p>BUT neither could <hi>Impeachments,</hi> extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary as they were, ſerve their Turn: They had recourſe to Bills of <hi>Attainder,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Attainders.</note> which are a ſummary way of robbing Men of their Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, Eſtates, and Lives, and which are ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom juſtifyable, excepting againſt thoſe, who maintain the Equity of that extraordinary Method of Arraignment.</p>
            <p>DURING the dependance of the <hi>Impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> and Bills of <hi>Attainder,</hi> there were uſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er'd into the Houſe with great Solemnity, Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts of <hi>Plots</hi> againſt the Government, and formidable Stories of Invaſions, on purpoſe to alarm the timerous, to enflame the Angry, to afford a pretext for augmenting the Forces, the Command whereof, was to be in their Hands, and to multiply Taxes for the Beneſit of the Advocates for the Cauſe, and the Creatures of the principal Men.</p>
            <p>THOSE Diſtempers and Violences of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> naturally inſpired ſuch, as were to be the Sacrifice, with a Reſolution to defend themſelves. So the <hi>Civil War</hi> commenced,
<note place="margin">Civil War.</note> which was manifeſtly the effect of the Rage and Wickedneſs of the Managers in the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:58333:14"/>and of the Craft and Treachery of <hi>many about the King.</hi> And it was not deny'd by ſome of them, that they intended from the beginning, to drive Things to theſe Extremities, which they ſaid were neceſſary, to make the <hi>King a great King;</hi> though it was eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, their Deſigns were to make him their Slave, to alter the Frame of the Conſtitution, to govern by Force and a Standing Army, and to Oppreſs and Tyrannize over their Fellow-Subjects.</p>
            <p>WHEN they had got an Army and a Civil War, or Rebellion to their Mind, it was far from being their deſire to make a ſpeedy End of it; which was viſible from many Things, particularly from this, That they iſſu'd out no Proclamation of Pardon to thoſe, who ſhould lay down their Arms. Nor was it their Intereſt; the War, or the Pretence of it, was to bring about many <hi>great Things</hi> for them. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they apprchended that an Army of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhmen</hi> would hardly ſupport them in what they Projected,
<note place="margin">Foreign Army.</note> they invited a Body of <hi>Foreign</hi> Forces into the Heart of the Kingdom; and theſe they kept a long time after the Buſineſs was done, for which they were pretended to be call'd in; till at length, not out of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion to the Country, although heavily Tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for the Maintenance of the two Armies, and ſeverely oppreſſed by them, but purely, becauſe they had no further Work for them,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:58333:14"/>and were now able to walk alone, they dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs'd, and moſt liberally rewarded their Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Deliverers, as they term'd them.</p>
            <p>HAVING all the Money of the Kingdom at their diſpoſal, the Civil Power, and two Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies well appointed, it was no wonder Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry declared on their Side; which they uſed with the Inſolence and Barbarity to be expected from them.
<note place="margin">Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> And if there had been any Diſpoſition to heal the Wounds of a bleeding Nation, here had been a fair Field for ſo happy an Event. A frank and generous Pardon might have eſtabliſhed Tranquility; but this was the Terror of governing Men, and what they ſpurned at from their Souls. So they ſet themſelves to execute Rigor, as it were in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpight of the Senſe, and Wiſhes of Mankind, and of the Addreſſes of all thoſe, who might be ſuppoſed to have moſt Credit with the Perſecutors. But all Application ſeemed but to whet the Edge of Cruelty, many Parts of the Kingdom became the Scenes of their Butcheries, in cold Blood. The MANNER of one of thoſe was
<note n="*" place="bottom">Lord <hi>Clarendon.</hi> Hiſt.</note> 
               <hi>New, and without Example.</hi> Several Noble Perſons and others Surrendered to Mercy, having been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to it, through the Perſwaſions of the Commanding Officer who attacked the Town, in which they had unfortunately ſhut them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:58333:15"/>up. One or two of the Priſoners were preſently Shot for Example, under Pretence of <hi>Military Juſtice,</hi> the reſt
<note n="†" place="bottom">Lord <hi>Clarendon,</hi> Vol. 3. Pag, 137. and 204, 205, 206.</note> they reſerved to be more Publick Spectacles. They were brought up to <hi>London,</hi> treated with all the Ignominy that could be deviſed, Condemned, and many of them Executed: And ſuch an Alien to all Gallantry, was the Officer, who perſwaded them to Surrender, that either from the Virulence of his own Nature, or his Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to gratify his Maſters, or perhaps from both, he miſ-interpreted the Laws of Arms and of <hi>Nations,</hi> as if a <hi>Promiſe of Mercy</hi> did but <hi>exempt the Priſoners from the Fury of the Soldiers, or a Council of War.</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it were, it was an odious Caſe; and the Sufferers were not more pitied, than he and his Patrons were loaded with Execrations of all Sorts.</p>
            <p>NOT content with the many Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in ſeveral Parts of the Kindgom, the <hi>Parliament</hi> ſeized upon all the Eſtates of the Delinquents, and appointed a <hi>Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of <hi>Sequeſtrators,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtrators.</note> to enquire into the Effects of the Perſons they had a mind ſhould forfeit: This Commiſſion was made up of ſeveral of the moſt <hi>Corrupt</hi> and Inhuman of the whole Tribe, and had a Power, almoſt unlimited, thrown into their Hands, by which they miſerably grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:58333:15"/>all ſorts of People who had any thing to do with them.</p>
            <p>IT is difficult to conceive the groſs Abuſes theſe Men were guilty of: Neither the Tears and Cries of innocent, ſtarving Widows and Orphans, the Equity of the Cauſe, or their own ſatiety in Injuſtice and Severities, could make them relax from their Reſolution to do wrong. They undertook the Employment for that purpoſe; and their Conſciences and Inclinations were of that mold, not to give them leave to receive their Hire for ſo agrecable a Work, and to do it by halves.</p>
            <p>WHILST they were ſo happily poſſeſs'd of a Rebellion to carry on their Purpoſes, many Perſons of all Ranks were ſeized, and without any Forms of Law, or knowing their Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, and even without any Accuſation at all, were detained a long time in Priſon; their Friends and Relations prohibited to come near them, and they not permitted to have common Neceſſaries: Which Invaſion of Men's Rights was ſo univerſally practis'd throughout the Kingdom; it would fill a Volume to enumerate how many Perſons and Families were undone by it. I have ſeen a Manuſcript in the Hands of a Nobleman, containing the Names of the Oppreſſors, and an account of Thouſands of Innocent People, many of them Perſons of diſtinction, who ſuffered in their Health, Eſtates, and ſeveral who loſt their Lives by that illegal Method
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:58333:16"/>of Impriſoning, <hi>ad arbitrium.</hi> Which ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly was a great Argument, among a Multitude of others, of the dangerous Conſequence of breaking in upon the Fences of National Freedom. Not but that it is a prudent piece of Policy in all Governments, to ſtrengthen themſelves by ſecuring the Perſons of ſuch Enemies, as Plot their overthrow: But the Methods, thoſe Men made uſe of, were wholly unjuſtifiable, and wou'd have rendered them odious, tho' they had done nothing elſe, that was bad. For, what elſe could be ſaid of them and their Proceedings, but that the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervators of the Liberty of their Countrymen, not only gave up the chief Security thereof, which was the <hi>Habeas-Corpus;</hi> but ſhewed the Example themſelves to others to ſtrike at the Root of the Conſtitution?</p>
            <p>As the <hi>Army</hi> was their chief Support,
<note place="margin">A Standing Army.</note> they ſtudied all ways of pleaſing the Officers, and ſubjecting the Common Soldiers to anſwer their Ends. In order to the firſt of theſe, they paid them well, indulged them in all kinds of Licenſe, that a victorious Army are prone to; and then to quiet their Minds againſt the Fear of Suits or Proſecutions for their Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages, they kindly gave them a <hi>Bill</hi> of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnity</hi> for their ſole Uſe and Protection; and to juſtify all the Inſults and Barbarities they had committed, which were without Number. And when the Country became
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:58333:16"/>exhauſted by Taxes,
<note place="margin">Modelling the Army which they called Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banding.</note> and that all Men cried out to have the Army reduced, they fell upon a Scheme to favour their good Friends, and yet ſeem to comply with the Wiſhes and Wants of the People: which was to model, the Army ſo, as to keep up a <hi>great Number</hi> of <hi>Officers,</hi> and fewer Soldiers. By which means, they had a new Opportunity of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging that Body of thoſe they diſliked, they gratified their Friends, and ſtill retained the ſame Power to do Miſchief, and continued the ſame Oppreſſion upon the Country.</p>
            <p>IN Order to ſubdue the Spirits of the Common Soldiers to all their Uſes, they ſet up <hi>Martial Law,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Martial Law in Time of Peace.</note> independent of the Civil Magiſtrate, and in Times of Peace. This was to act fairly, and take off the Maſque at once; ſince it was in effect to ſet up for a Military Government without further Ceremony. For how averſe ſoever the Soldiers might be to trample upon the Laws and Liberties of their Countrymen, they were by <hi>Martial Law</hi> to be compelled to it: a Refuſal to ſerve for ſuch Purpoſes was thereby interpreted <hi>Mutiny;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mutiny.</note> for which they were inſtantly to be Shot, being deprived of the Benefit of the Laws of the Land, and totally excluded from their Right by <hi>Magna-Charta</hi> to an equal Tryal by a Jury of their Neighbours. And the Hardſhip was ſtill the greater upon the Common Soldiers, that though their Country ſhould not require
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:58333:17"/>their Service, and that they ſhould deſire to retreat to their Homes, their Families, or ſome honeſt Occupation, it was not in their Power; but they were to be put to Death for <hi>Deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deſertion.</note> to attempt a Delivery from Idleneſs and Servitude. Thus by Virtue of this Law, the Soldier became firſt enſlaved, in order after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to bring the Country under Bondage: Whilſt the Officers gained a Dominion, which they abuſed according to the Tyranny of their Natures and the Pride of Upſtarts; and this perhaps might make common Soldiers the more ready to bring their Fellow Subjects in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Slavery, that they might all be upon an equal Foot: For the ſame Purpoſe, they put the <hi>Militia</hi> under new Regulations, and into the Hands of Men, notorious for Animoſity, againſt the Conſtitution in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> or of ſo little Intereſt or Stake in their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, that they might be depended upon, as proper Inſtruments to bring it into Subjection.</p>
            <p>UNDER the Notion of ſuppreſſing <hi>Tumults and Riots,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tumults, and Riots.</note> they took all Arbitrary Meaſures to prevent honeſt Men from meeting and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſing freely together; at the ſame time that they encouraged a ſeditious Number of Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows in the City, to inſult the well-meaning Freemen and Citizens, who they imagined diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liked their Proceedings. They dreaded leſt the True <hi>Engliſh</hi> Spirit ſhould revolt againſt ſuch Task-Maſters; therefore, by that and ſome other
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:58333:17"/>terrible Ordinances, they did, what in them lay, to ſink the Genius of the People into that abject Tameneſs, that might make them more eaſily ſubmit their Necks to the Yoke prepared for them. To this, were added many Examples of their Severity againſt thoſe, who had fallen under their Diſpleaſure. For they found out a way of <hi>trying</hi> them, not in their own Country where their Characters were known, nor in the Places where the Offences were committed; but here in <hi>London,</hi> where none of the <hi>Jury</hi> perhaps had eyer heard of them,
<note place="margin">Illega<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Try<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> untill called upon for this particular Service; which was a Method againſt all Rules of common Juſtice. Neither could it be excuſed by any pretended Exigences of the State, nor the Evil ballanced by any Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage thoſe Men could propoſe from the breach of the Conſtitution in ſo Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal a Point: But they knew they did not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to be loved, ſo they took Care to be feared; as Men, who had Power, and would uſe it without regard to God or Man.</p>
            <p>BUT one of the moſt fatal and confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Parts of their whole Management,
<note place="margin">Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> was the Act for <hi>Continuing</hi> themſelves; which was ſince called the Act for the <hi>Perpetual Parliament.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">The Act for the <hi>Perpetual Parliamant</hi> as it is called. <hi>Pag.</hi> 204, <hi>Clar.</hi> Fol. 1ſt Vol.</note> This was directly contrary to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:58333:18"/>the Intent and Reaſons of the
<note n="†" place="bottom">A Bill for the <hi>Triennial Parliament,</hi> paſſed. <hi>Pag.</hi> 165, <hi>Clar.</hi> Fol. 1ſt Vol.</note> 
               <hi>Triennial Act,</hi> which they had before affected to be ſo fond of, and which the Nation afterwards had ample Reaſon to wiſh had been always pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved Sacred and Inviolable.</p>
            <p>IT is not to be repreſented, what a Flood of Calamities overwhelmed the King and Kingdom, from this accurſed Act. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this, the ſworn Managers, could not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly have gone through with their Work. Their Power indeed would have laſted too long, but it would have had a Period with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>three Tears;</hi> and the Fear of their being call'd to Account at the expiration of that Time for paſt Crimes, might have put ſome Bounds to their Wickedneſs. But the <hi>length<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ening</hi> the <hi>Time</hi> of their <hi>Domination</hi> enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged their Views, and they looked upon Juſtice to be as remote in this, as in another World, Hence, the loweſt and meaneſt Creatures of that Aſſembly extended their Ambition, copi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed after their Elders and <hi>Superiors</hi> in <hi>Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and dreamed of no leſs, than of ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into Lords and Peers of the Realm; and hence it happened, that all Methods, how Scandalous ſoever, of acquiring Riches for the Members, were entertained in the Houſe with that Joy and Ardor, which left little or no Room for Contradiction.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:58333:18"/>
            <p>HENCE befell amongſt an infinite Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of other Miſchiefs, <hi>one</hi> of ſuch a mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous Nature, it will be an everlaſting Blot upon the Senſe as well as the Virtue of the Nation; as it was at that Time a heavy Judgment upon it from Heaven: A general Infatuation ſeemed to have ſeized Men; for although many there were, who heartily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liked both the Thing, and the manner of it, and deteſted the Iniquity of the <hi>Contrivers,</hi> yet the Parliament paſſed it in great Gaiety, and found Inſtruments as wicked as themſelves to <hi>execute</hi> it. <hi>Is habitus animorum fuit, ut preſſimum facinus auderent pauci, pleures vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, omnes paterentur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>SOME of the chief Actors in that <hi>black-Affair</hi> were taken untimely away to anſwer for it elſewhere, before they could be brought to Trial here: Others by other means eſcaped the Hands of the Miniſters of Juſtice; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed all of them found much milder Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment than they deſerved.</p>
            <p>BUT this Evil, great as it was, was but one, out of many, that flowed from the Continuance of that CORRUPT Parliament. There were ſome Wiſe Men ſaw the ill Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences of that <hi>perpetuating Act,</hi> and the Reaſons they gave againſt it were ſufficiently juſtified by the Sequel of Things: But no Mortal could have foreſeen all the Ill it really
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:58333:19"/>produced. How terrible then muſt that Act have been, which was calculated to bring forth many Miſchiefs unavoidable from the Nature of it, and which might, as in Truth it did, beget many more, that no Man could have conceived, if they had not happened. It is true the Bill had the Royal Aſſent, but his Majeſty did not weigh the Conſequences of it, and the Craft of the Propoſers; nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the Blow it gave to his own Prerogative, by inveſting Men in Power, who could have no Temptation to deſire it, but the Purpoſe to abuſe it; which they did to the full, and yet had the Art to load his Majeſty as the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of all thoſe Violences, and to render him the Object of the Popular Rage and Invectives.</p>
            <p>IN all this Tinie that they were heaping Acts one upon another againſt the Laws of the Land, of Reaſon, and Nature, they were alſo <hi>multiplying Taxes</hi> as faſt as they could. There was a <hi>Committee of Accounts</hi> (a ſad Pack indeed!
<note place="margin">Increaſe of Taxes.</note>) whoſe Trade it was to ſquan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der away the <hi>Publick</hi> Money,
<note place="margin">Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee of Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts.</note> and to bring the <hi>Publick</hi> ſtill farther into Debt. <hi>Arrears, Services, Deficiencies, Subſidies</hi> to <hi>Foreigners,</hi> with a thouſand other Pretences, were every Day made the Ground for new Impoſitions upon the poor Country; new Employments were created for their Tools; and Rewards; that is, <hi>Penſions</hi> and <hi>Bribes,</hi> were ſcattered
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:58333:19"/>up and down, though the Treaſury was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely empty; nay, though the Country was beggared, and Trade which ſhould bring in Money, was neglected, and wantonly thrown into other Nations. I am told a Gentleman now living, hath been curious enough, to take an Account of the ſeveral Sums thoſe Plunderers laviſhed away from the Publick, and that the Sums voted for the Service of but one Year exceeded all that had been gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for thrice the ſame Period by the moſt prodigal of their Prececeſſors; yet that Year was a Year of Peace too, and the People were never ſo miſerably Poor as then.</p>
            <p>IT would puzzle a Man to gueſs, what ſort of Notions thoſe People at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> could have. They were eternally told of the Miſery of the Country, they heard ſcarce any thing out of the Houſe, but the Groans of the Suffering People; yet as ſoon as they got within <hi>thoſe Walls,</hi> they voted away ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious Sums, at ſuch a mercyleſs rate, one would think they took it to be the Duty of their Place, to Scourge and Plague the Land.</p>
            <p>How little they conſidered the Intereſt of <hi>England</hi> with reſpect to Foreign States ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Clar.</hi> Vol. 3. p. 170. In the Year 1658, and 1659. <hi>hislock</hi> alſo.</note> from many Inſtances. They un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonably
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:58333:20"/>ſeaſonably ſent a <hi>Fleet</hi> at vaſt Expences into the <hi>Sound,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Fleet ſent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nto the <hi>Baltick.</hi>
               </note> under Pretence of mediating a Peace between the <hi>Northern</hi> Powers; but they acted the Mediators ſo ill, it was eaſily ſeen they made themſelves a Party in the Quarrel. And which was ſtill worſe, they join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with <hi>France</hi> in a War againſt <hi>Spain,</hi> to the Ruin of the Trade and Commerce of <hi>England,</hi> and contrary to all Rules of Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and good Senſe, which at that Time ſhould have engaged them rather to be <hi>Neuters,</hi> or if they would needs meddle in the War,
<note place="margin">A War a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Spain</hi>
               </note> it ſhould have been, to have raiſed <hi>Spain</hi> to be a Ballance againſt the growing Power of the <hi>French</hi> Monarchy; which, though under a Minority, was then likely enough to be one Day a formidable Enemy to <hi>England.</hi> But thoſe unskilful Rulers, caſt their Politicks only for the Day, how for the preſent they might keep their Power and Dominion over their Subjects, and ſo left Poſterity under the many Preſſures they had Treaſured up for them.</p>
            <p>IT cannot be thought but from ſo long a Train of Abuſes and Corruptions, the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment muſt have drawn upon it ſelf great <hi>Odium.</hi> The Nation ſuffered with Impatience the Tyranny of ſuch a profligate Sett, who plainly aimed at nothing leſs than to ride and vex, and harraſs the three Kingdoms for ever, this ſeemed the more inſupportable, becauſe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:58333:20"/>by the long execution of Power, their Perſons became perfectly well known, and of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, grew contemptible. Every Day produced ſome ſharp Pamphlet or other againſt them: To prevent this,
<note place="margin">A Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mittee Pamph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> they appointed a <hi>Committee</hi> to find out and Examine Printers and Authors, and as far as they could, to take away the Liberty of the Preſs; purſuant to which, ſeveral Printers and poor Hawkers were illegally Seized and Confined, and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Severely handled, at the Pleaſure of thoſe deſpicable Tyrants. But this had the uſual Effect in ſuch Caſes; they were more and more pelted, more and more deſpiſed. The Women and Children in the Streets, and their own Footmen in the Lobby of the Houſe agreed in the ſame Appellation of them, calling them a COMPANY OF ROGUES.
<note n="*" place="bottom">Whitlock p. 305.</note>
            </p>
            <p>DIVERS <hi>Widows,</hi> and other <hi>Creditors
<note n="†" place="margin">Ibid. 193.</note> of the Parliament,</hi> flocked to the Houſe,
<note place="margin">Clamo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> againſt Parliam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and in a rude and impetuous Manner, cried out to the Members — PAY US OUR MONEY — JUSTICE — JUSTICE — the RUMP — the RUMP, <hi>ſeeming ready to tear their Cloaths from off their Backs</hi>; inſomuch, that thoſe who had for ſo many Years Lorded over the three Kingdoms, were forced to ſend for Guards for a Defence, againſt a Parcel of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:58333:21"/>Women. Addreſſes from moſt of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Cities and Shires were ſent againſt them, renouncing them for Repreſentatives, and expreſſing the greateſt Abhorrence of their Perſons and Actions; until being now grown the Averſion and Scorn of the World, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence was pleaſed to diſſolve the Charm, that had bound theſe Nations under the Rule and Diſclpline of ſuch Wretches.</p>
            <p>ONE may form an Idea, to what a pitch of Deteſtation and Contempt that Houſe of Commons was arrived, from hence, that the moſt unpopular Man in the Kingdom became generally acceptable,
<note place="margin">Parliament in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt.</note> only becauſe he treated them as they merited. <hi>He loaded them</hi> (as
<note n="*" place="bottom">Ludlow.</note> one of themſelves mentions) <hi>with the vileſt Reproaches, charging them not to have a Heart to do any thing for the</hi> PUBLICK GOOD, <hi>to have eſpouſed a</hi> CORRUPT IN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TEREST, &amp;c. <hi>the Supporters of Tyranny and Oppreſſion, accuſing them of an Intention to</hi> PERPETUATE THEMSELVES IN POW<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ER. And when a <hi>Principal Member</hi> did but mention the Words <hi>Morality</hi> and <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non Honeſty,</hi> the other thought them ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper from his Mouth, he fell into an Exclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Contempt, crying out, <hi>The Lord deliver me from</hi> —</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:58333:21"/>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Whitlock.</note> ANOTHER of their Writers, who was alſo of the Houſe, gives much the ſame Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of that Paſſage, he relates, That the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, above hinted at, told the Houſe, That <hi>they had Sate long enough unleſs they had done more Good,</hi> That <hi>they were</hi> CORRUPT, UN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>JUST, <hi>and</hi> SCANDALOUS, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That <hi>it was not fit they ſhould ſit, as a Parliament, any longer,</hi> with a good deal more to the ſame Purpoſe, ſo he <hi>bid them be gone, and all of them tamely departed the Houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>SUCH was the Fate of the memorable <hi>Rump;</hi> upon which, this Author makes ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Obſervations of the Uncertainty of Worldly Things. They afterwards revived a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and had ſome glimmering Hopes of their Continuance: but their Hearts were quite broken by a final Diſſclution
<note n="†" place="bottom">Lord <hi>Clarendon</hi>'s Hiſt.</note> 
               <hi>to the unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Joy of all the reſt of the Kingdom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Parliamer diſſolved.</note> to whom they had been ſo long a moſt uncome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly irkſome Burthen, and <hi>who, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their very different Affections, Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Deſigns, were unanimous in their Wearineſs and Deteſtation of the</hi> LONG PARLIAMENT; which was obvious from the Multitude of Reproachful Addreſſes
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:58333:22"/>againſt them, and from the Behaviour of the City of <hi>London</hi> towards them a little before they were diſſolved.
<note place="margin">Joythere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon.</note> For, <hi>there could be no Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Fancy, Wit, or Ribaldry, that was not exerciſed</hi> by the Citizens and their Appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices, <hi>to defame them. As ſoon as the Evening was come, there was a continual Light of Bone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fires throughout the City and Suburbs, with ſuch an univerſal Exclamation of Joy, as had never been known, and cannot be expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; with ſuch ridiculous Signs of Scorn and Contempt of the Parliament, as teſtified the No-regard, or rather, the notable Deteſtation they had of it; here being ſcarce a Bonefire, at which they did not roaſt a Rump, and Pieces of Fleſh made like one,</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>which they ſaid, was for the</hi> CELEBRATION OF THE FUNERAL OF THE PARLIAMENT.</q>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:58333:22"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
